Guide to the Henry Barnard Papers 1765-1935 (Bulk 1830-1899) MSS.033
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series IV: Printed Material
  - unspecified
    - Clippings, Pamphlets, and Announcements, 1850-1881, (Bulk: 1850-1869) (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Includes "An Inaugural Address Delivered in the Senate Chamber of the Capitol before the Board of Regents of the [Wisconsin] State University" by E.S. Carr, 1856, January 16; "Barnard's Educational Labors," unknown author/source [1858]; "Circular" advertising Barnard's American Journal of Education by Thomas W. Bicknell, 1881; Photocopied newspaper article "Professor Henry Barnard," from The Daily Crescent, New Orleans, 1851, June 10, (index number 2-2787); Photocopy of newspaper article "Honorable Henry Barnard" by Lydia H. Sigourney, 1854, September (index number 2-3574); 3 "Notices" regarding special meetings of the Board of Trustees at Watkinson Library, 1863; 2 copies of an announcement for the Annual Meeting of the National Teacher's Association by W.E. Sheldon, 1863, June 20, with handwritten notes on the reverse of both; 2 further "Notices" from the Watkinson Library, also 1863; Printed message from John Eaton, Jr., 1868, Sept. 16; Incomplete "Report of Committee on Education and Labor to the House of Representatives," by S.F. Cary, 1869, February 16.
    - Clippings and Advertisements, 1870-1879 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Includes: "Education in District of Columbia: Letter of Commissioner of Education," by Henry Barnard, 1870, January 19; Title pages and table of contents from the American Journal of Education, vol. 9 of the National Series (vol. 24 of the entire series), 1874-5; "Centenniel Growth in Nationality, Industries, and Education," unknown author, 1876, July 4; "Retrospect and Prospect-1878," extracts from letters exchanged by R.H. Quick and Henry Barnard printed in the American Journal of Education, 1878; "Paris Exposition, 1878, Award of Gold and Silver Medals," unknown author/ source; 2 advertisements for "Barnard's American Journal of Education," unknown authors, 1878; "Program of Exercises for the Meeting of the National Educational Association to be Held at Philadelphia, July 29, 30, and 31, 1879," unknown author.
    - Clippings and Advertisements, 1880-1889 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Includes multiple copies of "Circular" advertising the American Journal of Education, by Thomas Bicknell, 1881; "Henry Barnard in Connecticut" by Thomas Bicknell, 1881, with "Henry Barnard- The American Educator" by John D. Philbrick, from the Massachusetts Teacher, 1858, appended; "Connecticut Schools and Education," by John W. Stedman, 1881; "Barnard's Encyclopedia of Education, Appeal by Miss Peabody," by Elizabeth P. Peabody, [1881]; "From the Record of the Class of 1830," [W.R. Cone], [1885]; "Connecticut Schools and Educators, Letter from Henry Barnard" by Henry Barnard, 1886; "Folk Lore Publication Society," by William Wells Newell, 1887; "American Library of Education and Schools," by Henry Barnard, 1887; Portion of a publication sent to Henry Barnard by R. H. Quick, 1889; "Rev. A.D. Mayo's Ministry of Education in the South", with testimonials from John Eaton, N.H.R. Dawson, J.L.M. Curry, William T. Harris, Atticus G. Haywood, 1889.
    - Clippings, 1890-1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Includes "Henry Barnard: the Nestor of American Education" by James L. Hughes (index number: 11421); "Table of Contents" from Pestalozzi and Swiss Pedagogy by Henry Barnard;Circuit Rider of the American Schools: Albert Edward Winship by George P. Winship; Printed card (index number 11729); An advertisement for the Lyceum Theatre's production of "Nathan Hale" ca. 1899 (index number: 11719); Advertisement for [D]evil's Island ca. 1899 (index number: 11720); printed page, origin unknown, describing two recognitions of Barnard in education literature of 1890 (index number 11716); and subscription offer for a "A Weekly Library for 5 Cents a Week" (index number: 11732).
    - Clippings, 1899, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Includes "Instruction by Correspondence," by E.F. Ware, undated; "Index" from Reminiscences by John Hooker, 1899; Photocopy of printed version of a letter to Henry Barnard from Earl Barnes; "University of Cambridge," unknown author, undated; "The Co-Operation of Parents Solicited by the Teacher of Their Children," from Educational Tracts No. 9, unknown author, undated; "Whittier and the New England Review," by S.T.P., undated; "Essentials," by W.W. Stetson, undated; "Circular of the Board of Normal School Regents of the State of Wisconsin," unknown author, undated; "To the Teachers and Controllers of Public Schools," by Grigg, Elliot, and Co., undated; "Prospectus of the National Society of Literature and Science," Unknown author, undated; Extract from "A Brief History of the Rhode Island Institute of Instruction, from 1844 to 1874," by Edwin M. Stone, undated; Typescript summary of a survey published in "Revue de l'Instruction Publique" by Alphonse LeRoy, unknown author, undated; Photocopies of newspaper articles regarding Henry Barnard; "The Practical Spelling Book," by T.H. Gallaudet and Horace Hooker, undated; "Dr. Henry Barnard's Standard Educational Publications," unknown author, undated; "Table of Contents" for Christianity in Education, Edited by Henry Barnard (index number: 1077); "Sur le Sentiment de l'honnete dans les Enfants" by Luigi Anfosso, undated; "Abstract of a Paper on the Psychic Unit," by William S. Wadsworth, undated; "Influence de l'age des Parents sur les Caracteres Psycho-Physiques des Enfants," by Antoine Marro, undated; "Die Sprache des Kindes und der Naturvolker," by H. Gutzmann, undated; "Mr. Tefft's Remarks," undated (index number: 11740); "The Quarterly Register of Current History," by The Evening News Association, undated (index number: 11741).
    - Certificates for Gifts, 1853; 1863; [1897] (Box 9, Folder 6)
      From Brown University Library, 1853 (Index number: 3344); The Public Library of the City of Boston, 1863; and an official Birthday Greeting from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, from C.K. Adams, [1897].
    - Clippings, [1888], 1896, 1897, 1899, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Includes photocopy of "Henry Barnard," by Albert E. Winship, from Christian Register, 1896; photocopy of "The Barnard Celebration," by Will S. Monroe, undated; Photocopy of "In Dr. Barnard's Honor," unknown author, from the Yale Alumni Weekly, 1897; Photocopy of newspaper article "Henry Barnard," unknown author, 1896; Photocopy of newspaper article "The Founder of Schools," unknown author, 1899; Photocopy of newspaper article "Barnard, Henry," unknown author, 1888.
- Series V: Letters in Other Collections
  - unspecified
    - Wisconsin Historical Society, letters from Henry Barnard to Lyman C. Draper and J.H. Armsby, 1856-1858 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1829-1833 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1834-1837 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1838-1849 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1855-1860, 1881-1882 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Addenda
  - unspecified
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1823-1836 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1838-1839 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1840-1841 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1842-1843 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1844-1845 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1846-1848 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1849-1852 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1853-1855 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1856-1859 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1860-1869 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1870-1879 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1880-1889 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1890-1896 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1897-1899 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard and Monroe's Correspondence, 1900-1935, Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
      Includes items stamped with alphabetical index numbers 11754, 11747, 11746
- Series VII: Photograph File
  - unspecified
    - A-Bar, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Barnard, Henry, 1883, 1893, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Barnes-Bz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Ca-Ch, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Ci-Coo, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Cop-Cz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - D-Di, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Dickinson, John W., Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Dj-Dz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - E, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - F, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - G-Gn, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Go-Gz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - H-Ham, Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Han-Haz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Hb-Hn, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Ho-Hos, Undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Hot-Hu, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Hughes, Ada; Hughes, James, Undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Huh-Hz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - I-J, Undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - K-Ki, Undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Kj-Kz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - L-Li, Undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Lj-Lz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - M-Maq, Undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Mar, Undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Mas-Mel, Undated (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Meleney, Clarence, Undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Mem-Mez, Undated (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Mf-Mow, Undated (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Mowry, Dr. William A., Undated (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Mox-Mz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - N, Undated (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - O, Undated (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - P-Pe, Undated (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Pf-Pz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - Q, Undated (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - R, Undated (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - S-Se, Undated (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - Sf-Sk, Undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - Sm-Sz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - T, Undated (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - U, Undated (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - V, Undated (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - W-Wh, Undated (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Wi-Wz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 47)
    - Y-Z; Miscellaneous photograph of Henry Barnard's home, Undated (Box 12, Folder 48)
    - Photocopies A-B, Undated (Box 12, Folder 49)